[playful jingle]
[uplifting music]
[crowd cheering]
[narrator] That distance
is what gives power to time.
That distance determines
the value of a person.
That distance is what I bet my life on.
-That distance is 100 meters.
-[cheering fades]
[race starter] Set…
[bugle call]
[crowd cheering]
[silence]
[panting]
[gasping]
TOGASHI
[friend] Togashi, you could totally
become the best in the whole world.
I don't know.
Running against us
must not be any fun for you.
I don't think like that 'cause I normally
have fun running against anyone.
You're the fastest sixth grader
in all of Japan!
[friend]
You're so whatever about it, Togashi.
[Togashi] You think so?
[train rattling on track]
[birds chirping]
-[boy gasping]
-Huh?
[panting, groans]
[coughing]
Are…
you okay?
Yeah… I'm… okay.
[coughing softly]
But you seem like
you're about to die any second now.
-[coughs] No, I'm fine.
-You're not okay. You're out of breath.
[gasps, coughs]
I'm used to it. [heavy breathing]
This is normal for me.
Normal?
[sniffs, sighs]
[grunts, groaning]
-Thanks a lot. [sighs]
-Sure.
[sighs, panting]
Uh…
[panting]
-[students chattering]
-[bell chiming]
[door opens]
Hmm? [gasps]
Alright, time to settle down, everyone.
We have a new classmate joining us today.
I know him.
You do?
He's the transfer student
that I mentioned. This is Komiya.
Alright. Let's make him feel welcome.
I, um…
Huh? [chuckles]
Go on, say hi.
Um… Hi… My name's…
Nice to meet you. I'm Komiya.
[girl] I can't hear you!
Me neither. Can you repeat it louder?
[teacher sighs] Come on, guys.
What did I just say?
[boy] But how can I welcome him
if I don't even know what his name is?
-[boy laughs]
-[teacher] That's enough, Genta.
[students laughing]
[teacher] The interior angles
in a triangle add up to 180 degrees.
Some think it's 360. That is incorrect.
Now parallelograms are a bit tricky,
so pay attention.
[whistle blows]
[panting]
[coach] Okay, next.
Oh, man. What'll I do if I lose?
Get set…
[whistle blows]
[panting]
[gasping]
[whistle blows]
[panting]
[whooshing]
Wow.
-[boy 1] Bye!
-[boy 2] Bye. See you tomorrow!
[sighs]
[clock ticking]
[panting in distance]
Hmm?
[woman speaks indistinctly]
[panting]
Komiya!
[man grunts]
[Togashi] Komiya!
Hey, wait up!
Komiya!
Hold on!
Togashi…
[gasping]
What happened? Where am I?
You're in my neighborhood right now.
I'll walk you to that riverbank
we were at before.
So, do you like to run?
Not really. It's pretty hard.
Okay, then why are you always running?
'Cause it gets blurred.
What do you mean? What's blurred?
-The world.
-[gentle music]
When I run, it hurts,
more than reality, so it distracts me.
See you.
Okay, but…
-if that's your reason for running,
-[gasps]
don't you think you're misusing it?
-Misusing it?
-[music concludes]
Oh, uh… How do I explain?
Well, running's all that I have.
Huh?
I'm a loner, I'm shy, I have no friends.
I'm never really sure
how to solve the problems in my life,
so I just keep running away.
I know it's only a temporary fix, though.
But running for that reason
is good enough for me.
So I keep doing it,
even though I know my problems
can't be solved by running.
But you're wrong about that, Komiya.
Huh?
It's true, you won't solve anything
by just coming out here and running.
But I know one thing.
And what is that?
There is one simple rule
that I believe in this world.
It's more than just a sport.
Running the 100-meter dash
faster than anyone else
can solve almost anything.
It can solve almost anything?
How can you be so sure about that?
Well, it's because… it works for me.
[Komiya] Uh… I see.
So then… the 100 meters…
Is it possible?
For me to get faster?
You're going to have
to decide that for yourself.
[pensive music]
That decision is mine.
[energetic theme music]
[theme music ends]
-[woman] Bye, everyone!
-[group] Bye!
-[boy] Togashi.
-[indistinct chatter]
You want to come play games
at Kawano's house?
Can't. Sorry, I have somewhere
to be today. Maybe next time.
[Togashi] See you tomorrow.
-Huh?
-How lame. He's no fun.
[panting]
That's it! Swing your arms more!
Imagine kicking the ground
as hard as you can!
[mid-tempo guitar music]
[laughter, chatter]
[gasps]
[Togashi] Get your knees higher.
-[music concludes]
-[chattering]
[boy] Hey, Togashi, want to game
at my house today?
Uh, unfortunately, I've already got plans.
-What? You're ditching us again?
-Sorry, I can't.
See you tomorrow.
I don't get why
he keeps bailing on us like this.
[panting]
Don't you get tired running everyday?
You're getting better,
but like, isn't it hard?
I'm okay. It's like the more I train,
the lighter my legs are starting to feel,
and it's even kind of fun.
Well, Sports Day is coming up, so you
should really take a day off to rest.
It seems like a waste to rest.
Besides, I need to learn more from you.
Yeah, but resting's
a part of training too.
[Togashi] Oh, and you should
really get some new shoes.
Oh yeah. Right.
Good thing I had arts and crafts today.
-I'll just wrap this around, then.
-[tape screeching]
No, no, wait, Komiya!
I don't think that's gonna…
[Komiya grunts] There, that should do it.
I don't know about that.
Your shoes look pretty ugly.
They feel fine now.
They're barely holding together.
Oh, is it because your parents
won't buy you a new pair?
No.
Actually, they keep telling me
they want to get me a new pair of shoes.
But because I've been running in these
for so long, I kinda wanna race in them.
Oh yeah. If I end up winning
the 100-meter dash,
does that mean I'll get a medal?
Huh? Yeah. One from the 100-yen store.
I'd like that.
I would love to win
a gold medal, just once.
That would be really nice.
[crowd cheering]
[announcer] The boys' 100-meter dash
will be beginning shortly.
[spectator] You guys can do it!
-[gunshot blasts]
-[crowd gasps, murmurs]
Wow, that kid's so fast.
That's Togashi, isn't it?
Everyone who's just finished,
please come this way.
What was the point of racing Togashi?
Because it's Sports Day, that's why.
Wait, where is Togashi?
-[Genta] Hey, new kid.
-[upbeat music]
Did all that training
help you get any faster?
[scoffs] Are you seriously
gonna run in those shoes?
Fine, ignore me.
[man] Hey, Togashi! Get over here!
[race starter] On your marks,
get set…
[jazzy mid-tempo music]
-[crowd cheering]
-[exhilarating music]
[laughing]
Come on, Komiya! Give it everything
you've got! Don't forget how fast you are!
[music intensifies]
[panting]
Yes!
[cheering]
[gasping]
[announcer] Up next will be
the 100-meter dash's award ceremony.
Congratulations.
[chattering]
[anchor] Yesterday at the National Junior
High School Track and Field Championships,
Takeru Nigami,
the son of the former
national team member,
won the boys' 100-meter dash.
This outstanding achievement
by the amazing second-year student
is making rather large waves
in the sports world.
-[Togashi] Excuse me.
-Hm?
Ah, Togashi.
Sorry to disrupt your lunch.
It's fine.
Here, take a look at this.
Ever heard of it?
Track and Field magazine?
[grunts]
[Komiya] That's so cool, Togashi.
Yeah, Mr. Tani told me about it.
It's for Track and Field Monthly.
[grunting]
An interview with Takeru Nigami?
Sounds awesome.
His school's nearby,
and he's a few years older, right?
Yeah, I think so.
[groans] Do you think
that you're faster than him?
Nah, Nigami's definitely faster than me.
[Komiya] Well, who knows?
Why don't you ask him to race for real,
instead of just pretending to do it
for the photo-op?
Right. There's no way
that's going to happen.
You're probably right.
[students chattering]
[indistinct chatter]
Togashi and Nigami
are going to race each other.
[boy] Wait, but he's older.
[woman] Mr. Nigami's just arrived.
-[Nigami] Sorry that I'm a little late.
-[gasps]
-[Nigami] Uh, no need to get up.
-Uh…
[grunts]
I've heard about you, Togashi.
My name's Nigami. Nice to meet you.
-Wow, it's really Nigami!
-He's older. You should probably use "Mr."
Now that you've both introduced
yourselves, shall we get started?
Of course, I'm ready, ma'am.
I'm ready to start too, ma'am.
Okay. Would you like to ask
your first question, Togashi?
Uh, yeah, sure.
Let's see now… First, uh…
Tell me, what made you decide to run?
Well, that's easy.
To win first place, of course.
How about you, Togashi?
Do you like running
because you're naturally faster
and that makes it fun for you?
Yeah, I guess so.
Me too. But once you take first, it's hard
to go back to just enjoying yourself.
Some part of you
must realize that, Togashi.
Committing your life
to that distance becomes the goal.
You have to run no matter what
and never give up.
[gasps]
[Nigami] You will be controlled
by your race results.
But running's ultimately
a simple thing to do.
If you want to belong
and stay in the game,
you have to be committed.
To win, you must have absolute devotion.
[huffing]
[helicopter whirring]
-[starting block clanks]
-[panting]
Oh, wow, he's got good form.
What do you think about his technique?
Look at his cadence, his balance, rhythm,
the way he shifts his weight.
It's hard to believe he's a sixth grader.
[Nigami] Fifty times.
Togashi, listen.
Any potential you think you've got,
you've got 50 times more.
-[reporter] That's quite a compliment.
-Uh, thank you.
That's nice of you to say.
[boy] Hey, they're about
to start the race!
The photographer and I will be positioned
right around the 40-meter mark.
So, no need to go all out after that.
-Got it.
-Right.
Thanks again for both
agreeing to take part in this.
[tense music]
[camera shutter clicking]
[reporter] On your marks…
Get set…
[dynamic energetic music]
[gasps]
Does that mean Togashi won?
Um, I don't know if it counts,
since Mr. Nigami stopped running halfway
after they took the photo.
[reporter] That worked out so great!
Thanks, I appreciate it.
We were able to get some fantastic shots.
The two of you made it look like
you were actually racing each other.
I was on the edge of my seat
watching you both.
This article's going to be a hit
thanks to you both.
[panting softly]
[Komiya] I know Nigami
stopped running halfway and everything,
but I think you would've beat him
if he kept going.
I don't know about that. The only reason
he was running was because of the photo.
Maybe he stopped because he knew
that he was gonna lose to you.
There's no way that's true.
When I was watching you guys,
you both seemed to be giving it your all.
Or at least to me,
it looked like you were, Togashi.
That's only because I don't know
how to hold back.
Whenever I run, I can't help
but try my hardest
and push myself to the finish line.
You know, I actually learned
something new today.
It made me realize
the real reason why I'm like this.
Do you want to know what I think?
I think you might just beat
Zaitsu's record one day.
Oh, geez. That may
be dreaming a little too big.
Togashi.
Is it okay if I ask you
for a favor right now?
What is it?
Could we do a 100-meter dash?
I want to race you.
Like now?
Mm. A real race.
[car engine revving]
The 100-meter mark is there.
Right under that tree, okay?
-[Komiya] Got it.
-[Togashi] The race will begin
when the train passes
that rail joint directly above us.
It's when we'll start running.
So, we'll go off that first sound, okay?
[grunts]
[suspenseful music]
[gasping]
Hey, Komiya. Are you okay?
[Komiya] Togashi, you eased off
at the end… [gasping] …right?
No, I went all out.
I told you I can't ease off.
[Komiya gasping] Thanks for that.
[groaning]
Well… goodbye, Togashi.
Yeah. See you tomorrow at school.
[gasps]
[train rumbling]
[indistinct chatter]
[teacher] Uh…
Good morning, everyone.
I'm afraid I have some bad news.
Unfortunately, I was just informed
that Komiya moved away yesterday,
and the move was related
to some family circumstances.
[gasps]
I know we're all disappointed,
since he was just settling in here.
Uh, how about we all write him a letter?
I'm sure he'd appreciate that.
[uplifting music]
[commentator]
What an incredible win by Togashi!
Going all out from the get-go like always,
that's still his trademark.
MITO SHINKIN BANK STADIUM
[announcer] In lane three, Sakaguchi,
from Nimani Daikon Junior High School.
This is the 100-meter dash finals,
the junior high championships.
All eyes are on Togashi,
the reigning champion of this event.
Since winning the championship
two years ago as a first-year student,
he's won every single meet
that he has entered so far.
He's definitely the favorite to win today.
You know, seeing Togashi on the track,
it calls to mind Zaitsu
from his junior high school years,
who, as you know,
is our current national record holder.
I agree with you there.
Track and field professionals
are taking interest,
curious about how high
Togashi's ceiling truly is.
-[race starter] On your marks…
-[commentator] Here we go, folks.
The finals for the boys' 100-meter dash
is about to commence.
[race starter] Set…
[horn blares]
-[gasping]
-[loud rumbling]
[cheering]
[bat clanks]
[panting]
The field's full.
Baseball club's hogging it.
-Isn't that Togashi over there?
-Who?
Hey, Aoi!
Togashi! I knew it!
Thats your name, right?
Yes.
So, did you join a club yet?
Or do you not want to?
Or maybe you're training
somewhere else on campus?
I'm sorry, didn't mean
to catch you off guard. I mean…
I heard rumors you enrolled here.
But why did you decide to come here?
A lot of elite schools
must have been scouting you.
Because it's close to home.
-That's the reason?
-[Togashi] Yes.
Oh. Sorry for asking so many questions.
That's fine. Excuse me.
-[Asakusa] Wait! Can I ask you a favor?
-Sorry, I can't.
But I haven't even…
I think I already know
what you're gonna ask.
Oh, no. It's nothing weird, I promise.
-[Aoi] Will you join the track?
-And I was right. See ya.
Wait, let's start over.
My name is Aoi Asakusa.
Togashi.
[chuckles] Yeah, I know.
Why aren't you interested
in the Track and Field club?
They currently have three members
who are officially in it.
And no one's really interested
in track and field anymore these days.
-[groans]
-Excuse me.
Oh.
[girl] Aoi!
[commentator] Track and field
professionals are taking interest,
curious about how high
Togashi's ceiling truly is.
-[girl] Hey, wait up.
-[boy] Hey.
-[boy] Morning.
-[girl] Morning.
[chattering]
[Shiina] Who's that?
I think it's Togashi.
Why is he sneaking around like that?
He's got a lot going on.
I'm sure it's tough on him.
[Togashi] Excuse me. Do you have
any of those special buns left?
Officially, they're sold out,
but hold on. [chuckles]
[gasps]
-[lady] Here, this is the last one.
-[gasps]
Are you serious? Thank you so much.
You're that track star.
Togashi, am I right?
That's me.
[lady] I heard you were attending
this school, so I--
-[Aoi] Hey.
-[both shriek]
Asakusa.
You remember my name. Cool!
Oh, you got one. I love those buns.
Oh, um… Here, take it.
No, it's okay!
Actually, do you think you could
please do me a favor instead?
Uh, what kind of favor?
-[Togashi] You want to see me run?
-[Asakusa] Yes.
But what for?
I want to run faster.
I know there's no way
I can be as fast as you,
but I might learn something
by watching you.
Look, I get it. This isn't exactly
a fair trade, but still…
And if I run for you,
will you stop asking for favors?
You have my word. I promise.
I'll just run from a standing--
Could you actually run
from a crouching start?
Sure.
Okay. You ready?
I'm ready. Go ahead.
[breathes deeply]
[panting]
What the… What was that?
Wow.
[gasps]
Amazing.
You truly are amazing.
It was silly of me to think
that I could learn from you.
You're basically super human.
Anyways, thanks.
Yeah. Mm… Yeah, sure.
I'm actually really relieved.
I heard rumors that you were injured
or going through something.
But I'm glad to see that's not the case.
[chuckles]
Thing is, I'm not talented.
Although I'm not sure
what makes me think that way.
Still, though,
I feel pretty strongly about this.
Doing track and field is a good thing.
But you, Togashi,
you're different from us.
You can do anything you want.
So, for you, you can enjoy every moment,
which is good 'cause that's sports.
[chuckles]
I'm sorry.
I wasn't trying to recruit you.
[chuckles]
[clock ticking]
NOTICE: TRACK AND FIELD CLUB IS CLOSING
[indistinct chattering]
Huh?
[Shiina] I can't believe we didn't get
a single person to sign up for the club.
[sighs] Well, track and field
isn't that popular of a sport.
[knock on door]
[Togashi] Hello?
[gasps]
[Asakusa] Togashi!
Oh, hi.
[Asakusa] They sent us
the notice a while ago,
but we just pretended
we didn't know about it.
Why is it shutting down?
Well, the rules are
you need to have a minimum of five members
to keep the club running.
Five, huh?
So, even if I join you,
that still isn't enough.
Togashi, what'd you just say?
Hold on. I'll be right back.
[door opens, closes]
He just said,
"Even if I joined," didn't he?
Uh, yeah.
-Are you actually serious?
-I am.
But… I heard that you were suffering
from health issues?
Right. That was just a rumor,
one that I started.
-What?
-Oh, uh, no, it's nothing.
The issue is each club needs
at least five members to stay open.
Sir, I don't want to be presumptuous here,
but I'm nationally ranked.
Would you please make an exception
just this once?
I know. I could…
But we should still follow the rules.
Is there anything I can do?
Tell you what.
I'll delay the closure for now.
Go try to win some events.
That'll justify keeping the club open.
I appreciate it, sir.
No way!
Do you know
when the next meet will be held?
Um, there's one soon.
It's with the neighboring schools.
Well, then we'll compete in that one.
-Thing is…
-What is it?
There's a mixed
four by two hundred-meter relay.
But we can just skip the relay, can't we?
It's just that that specific race is like
the main event of the whole competition.
I mean, they don't come out and say it,
but in reality,
it's more important to win that one
than any other event.
Yeah, that's true.
I participated in the relay when I was
a first-year student. It was intense.
I see. Then, that means if we win
the relay, it would be huge for the club.
But we'll still need
another guy to join us.
Wait a sec. Didn't you say
you had three members in total?
Is this third guy a real member?
Well, he would be an ideal candidate.
-But…
-I know.
So, uh… Thing is…
Yes?
Honestly, I'd be really thrilled
if you decided to join our club.
It's just…
You figured it out by now, haven't you?
I, uh… I was thinking
about quitting running.
The truth is,
I've been feeling stuck for some time.
[Togashi] I didn't place that well
in my last year of junior high.
I was scared of running and of quitting.
I was going in circles.
But then, yesterday,
when you asked me to run,
it reminded me of who I am.
And I am damn fast.
Because of you, I've decided
to give running another shot.
For that, I am forever grateful.
Thank you so much.
But… No need for all that.
I just wanted to watch you run.
That's all it really was.
Would you please allow me
to join the club?
Mm-hmm. Welcome
to Iwani Track and Field, Togashi.
[Shiina] I really wish
we could get him to do it.
So, he must be pretty good, huh?
Yeah. He hardly ever shows up
to the club, though.
We shouldn't be getting our hopes up,
but we can try
paying him a visit tomorrow.
Tomorrow? Why not right now?
[laidback music]
-[birds chirping]
-His place is at the top of this hill.
Okay.
[doorbell rings]
-[intercom clicks]
-[male voice] Yeah?
It's Asakusa.
What do you want?
I just wanted to chat.
Uh… Nigami?
Not a chance.
I figured that's what you would say to us.
Uh, how'd a famous athlete like you
end up enrolling at our high school?
Look who's talking. Seems like
I could ask you the same question.
Oh, well, that's 'cause…
I pushed myself too hard,
messed up my lower back doing it.
Because of that,
I couldn't run track and field anymore.
So, I transferred to my local high school.
Well then, why did you join
the track and field club at ours?
I'm only a member on paper
because I was forced to choose something.
And Asakusa wouldn't let up,
so I let her use my name.
[chuckles nervously]
You're back's still injured,
or have you recovered?
Are you able to run?
Don't know. I have no idea.
You never know until you try.
I'm not interested in trying.
So, you're happy with the way things are?
You know what I've learned?
In this world, there are some who will let
the 100 meters ruin their entire lives.
-[Togashi] So, um…
-Huh?
Do you have any time to spare today?
Time for what? For how long?
Ten seconds.
[Shiina] Ninety-eight, 99, and 100.
[shouts] Up to here!
Okay!
This won't even be a fair race
because I haven't run in half a year.
Asakusa, you give the signal.
-[Asakusa] Okay.
-[scoffs]
Ignoring me?
I bet you don't even know
how much faster you've become.
[Togashi] Fifty times.
-Probably about 50 times faster.
-[upbeat music]
Oh, yeah? Then we already know
who's gonna win.
Are the two of you ready to start?
-Uh-huh.
-I'm all set.
Then let's do this.
[Asakusa] On your marks!
Get set…
[energetic rock music]
-[panting]
-[music slows down]
Whoa!
-[gasping]
-[music concludes]
My time?
Twelve point thirteen seconds.
[gasping] Twelve, 13?
[scoffs]
[breathes deeply]
[aircraft whirring]
[inhales deeply]
Alright, so the event's
only three weeks away.
We should figure out
the racing order for the relay.
That'll give us a better idea
of how to train.
-[Komiya] Asakusa will go first.
-Got it.
-[Komiya] Next will be Shiina.
-Right.
I want you to do your best
on the first half.
-And our third runner, Togashi.
-Right.
Which means that leaves me as the anchor.
But shouldn't we let Togashi
be the anchor?
Uh, yeah.
I understand why that may seem
like the wiser choice to you.
But just trust me.
I promise I'll be in top form by then.
Sounds good.
Also, I'd like for us all
to use a down-sweep pass.
A down-sweep pass?
[Asakusa] It could potentially save us
time compared to the push-pass,
but there are downsides.
It's hard to coordinate
and make the exchange.
Yeah. Still, I think
it could be worth a try.
Exactly. I know it's a gamble,
but it's worth the risk.
Anything to beat Katsunishi, right?
Katsunishi?
Yeah. Nigami's old school.
Even more reason to beat them.
Yeah, they'll be
worthy opponents for sure.
[panting]
[Asakusa] It's no good.
The down-sweep's harder than I thought.
[Shiina] I might have started running
a little too soon.
[grunts]
So fast.
Those two are seriously on another level.
Let's try our best to keep up.
-Practice makes perfect.
-Mm.
[Shiina] Do you think it's okay
that Nigami's still out there training?
He's really pushing himself hard.
I know, right?
[grunting]
[Togashi] He has no choice but to push
himself to get back into shape.
But that doesn't change the fact
that he's got a ticking bomb on his back.
That's true.
What's with you today?
You seem even happier than usual.
[chuckles]
Of course I am!
After all, I'm gonna have a chance to run
with both the great Togashi and Nigami.
Suzume, we'll be running a relay race
with some pretty incredible members,
even though the club might close.
Well, now that you mention it,
I guess it is pretty cool.
Though I've only ever seen
Nigami be all grumpy,
and when I met Togashi,
he just seemed like an ordinary guy to me.
So, it didn't really feel that special.
[Togashi] Hold on, Shiina.
What kind of guy did you think I was?
[Shiina] Uh, well…
I guess you were like I imagined.
[Togashi] What does that mean?
[Shiina] Well, who cares. It's not gonna
matter if they end up closing our club.
[Togashi] I won't let that happen.
[upbeat music]
[inaudible]
MIXED 800 M RELAY
[Nigami panting]
Did you forget something?
I came to check on you and make sure
you're not working yourself too hard.
Oh, uh… I don't mean to imply
that you don't know
how to take care of yourself or anything.
But as you know…
it's easy to overtrain yourself.
You have to let your body recover.
[scoffs softly]
Yeah, that's not exactly helpful.
The race is in two days,
so I'll be careful.
Yeah, make sure to rest.
Well then, I'll get going now.
[Nigami] Why are you here?
What made you choose this school?
I'm sure that you
got offers from all over.
[chuckles]
Was it the pressure?
Before I knew it,
I became dependent on it.
For me, running was easy. It was the path
of least resistance. It made life simple.
The reason why I was wanted, valued,
and wasn't alone in this life
was because of these naturally fast legs
I was blessed with.
That makes two of us, Togashi.
[soft pensive music]
Because my father represented Japan
in the 100-meter dash,
I was put in the position
where I always had to win.
What I said to you back then
was something my father used to say.
If you want to belong
and stay in the game,
to win, you must have absolute devotion.
The pressure became unbearable.
And even though my body
was sending warning signs,
I was forced to ignore them.
On the track, what you gain in victory,
you lose in defeat.
If you're afraid of failure,
you have to keep winning,
even by a thousandth of a second.
[Nigami] That's the place
we have to go back to.
[birds chirping]
I thought that Togashi and Nigami
quit track and field.
Who knows?
It kind of feels
like everyone's watching them.
Well, that was bound to happen,
considering who they both are.
[Onomichi] Hey, 'sup?
-Hmm?
-Oh.
It's been a while.
Look who decided to finally
come out of their cave. Nigami.
Have you gotten a little faster
since the last time, Onomichi?
[scoffs]
Go ahead and keep talking like that
while you still can.
-[Onomichi] 'Cause the next time we race…
-Who's that?
Hirokazu Onomichi.
Nigami's rival and has been losing him
since grade school.
Hey, you, shut up!
You know I can hear you!
I seem to remember
that your excuse was always
that you were the youngest in our grade.
My birthday's in March. Yours is in April!
I'm almost a full year younger.
That's a huge handicap, man!
Age doesn't determine
if you have talent or not.
You were born on March 29th, I think.
Yeah, 361 days after you.
Whatever. I won't be defeated
by a shut-in like you today.
-[footsteps approaching]
-[man] What are you doing, Onomichi?
[gasps] Coach!
-Focus on the race.
-Right. Sorry, sir!
So, you ended up at Iwani High.
Morning, sir.
[Nigami] Today is the day.
These past three weeks,
we've done all the training we could.
To the other schools, this summer event
is more like a practice run for them.
But for us, this competition
determines our dignity.
Eight hundred meters.
Our hard work wasn't for nothing.
[crowd chattering]
He's actually pretty fast.
Way to go, rival.
Self-proclaimed.
Hey! Nigami, why don't you
run the 100-meter?
When did I even mention
running in the 100-meter?
Oh, I get it.
You're only focusing
on the 800-meter mixed relay, huh?
Bring it on! Yes! [laughs]
-[Togashi] Someone's energetic.
-[Nigami] He's just an idiot.
[announcer] The next event, the 800-meter
mixed relay will be beginning shortly.
-[boy 1] Hey, look, it's Togashi.
-[boy 2] Nigami's there too.
[boy 3] They're on the same team.
That's dope.
[suspenseful music]
[race starter] On your marks.
Set…
[dynamic music]
Aoi!
Suzume!
Nice!
We did it!
Geez. Keep the pace. Come on!
I'm sorry!
I can still catch up!
[upbeat dynamic music]
Let's race fair and square now.
Sorry, but the one I'm racing against
-is not you!
-Nigami!
[Shiina] Wait, the club's not closing?
Yeah, they were happy with how we did.
And now they want us
to compete in the summer meet.
The vice principal came
to tell me personally himself.
The vice principal?
So, I think he used to be
a track and field athlete back in the day.
And he went to school
with a coach at Katsunishi, right?
Yeah, I think I've heard that.
Well, either way, that's good news, right?
-Yeah.
-That's right.
Although I'm still
on the fence about this.
-[Nigami] Well, might as well run.
-[loud clang]
[crowd cheering]
[man] Check it out. Togashi
broke the championship record.
I bet he'll be crowned the winner
at nationals too.
No doubt. It's not like
he has any real competition.
[man] What about Nigami?
Nigami's not really a threat to him.
He barely qualified for nationals
by placing third.
There's also Tsuneda.
The kid's a solid runner, sure,
but I still think
he's no match for Togashi.
They say Togashi's been in a slump
for years and yet,
look at him, he's still out here
breaking all of his personal bests.
At this rate, he might beat Zaitsu's time.
-That'll make things--
-Huh?
Whoa, this can't be real! Somebody
just tied Zaitsu's national record!
-Who?
-It was Tsuneda, wasn't it?
No, it's some unknown first-year student.
[man] What's his name?
YEAR ONE KOMI…
[boy] Dang!
This school must be top tier.
Look at this line!
[sighs]
Yeah, I guess.
[boy] I'm Numano from Daito Junior High.
What's your name,
and which school are you from?
My name's Komiya,
but I've never been
in a track and field club.
What? Wait, so you're
just starting track and field?
And at such a top rank athletic school?
Yeah. But I've been training by myself
because I wanna join the school's team.
Oh, wow. And where'd you say
you live again?
Out by Nakatsu mountain.
So then it must be a hell of a train ride
just for you to commute here.
Yeah, so I just ride my bike.
What? And how long does that take you?
Two hours.
[soft mid-tempo music]
NISHIZAWA HIGH SCHOOL
[coach] Get set…
[whistle blows]
[panting]
Holy cow!
Tsuneda really is the best
of the best, isn't he?
[thuds softly]
Uh, hi. It's a pleasure to meet you all.
I'm Tsuneda, the captain…
It's hard to believe
he's only a second-year.
I understand that some of you may think
that this entry test sounds intimidating,
but wherever you run,
100 meters is 100 meters.
[coach] Get set…
[whistle blows]
Number 23 looks promising,
don't you think?
[groans] He almost had it.
He had a really strong start, though.
[boy] That first-year
was pretty impressive, huh?
Yeah, I guess he's the explosive type.
[gasping]
Hmm?
[Numano] Hey, Komiya!
Huh?
You were so insanely fast!
I mean, you seem to lose a little steam
towards the end, but…
but your start was incredible.
Your form was a little jerky, but…
you've got amazing balance. But…
you've got so much… [muffled warping]
[suspenseful music]
[Komiya gasping]
[whistle blows]
[sighs]
Komiya always seems
to lose velocity in the second half.
Yeah, he does.
[grunts]
[panting]
[girl] Captain, have you decided
which questions to ask?
Questions? Oh, right. For tomorrow.
[boy] Getting to interview Zaitsu
is gonna be amazing. What an opportunity.
[Tsuneda]
I mean, it's actually just a Q&A.
I'm only starting us off
because I'm the captain.
And then anyone can ask
whatever they want.
[boy chuckles] Well,
I'm too nervous to ask anything.
As I said before,
your high school years are important ones.
The time that you spend here
will be your foundation
and determine what path
your life will follow.
On that note,
Mr. Zaitsu, who's a five-time winner
of the national championships
and a proud alumnus of this school,
is giving you
a once-in-a-lifetime opportunity.
Please be respectful
and give him your full attention.
Without further ado, Mr. Zaitsu.
Don't think too deeply. Society's a joke.
And even if you do win,
keep attacking. That's it.
-[gasps]
-Are there any questions?
Yes.
You, go ahead.
My name is Tsuneda.
I'm the captain of our team.
I guess what I'd like to ask you is…
-Oh, uh, thank you.
-[microphone sound]
You've had an incredible career
and have a good number
of impressive records under your belt.
I mean, you're basically unbeatable.
So, what motivates you
to keep pushing yourself?
I'm a living thing. I will die,
never to be born again.
That's my motivation.
[gasps softly]
Uh, th-thank you very much, sir.
May I ask another question?
How do you mentally prepare yourself
when you're competing in the big races
on a national level?
Whenever I'm competing,
I can focus,
since I'm not afraid of losing.
But I also fear defeat,
since I desire results.
So your mood swings,
since those contrasting ideas
are each taking half of your focus?
Incorrect.
I benefit from 100% of both.
And you think like that
to avoid feeling nervous?
No, I think that way
so I can enjoy being nervous.
Um… Uh…
I see. Thank you for your answer.
Who's next?
[Komiya] I have a question.
Sure. Go ahead.
Hello. I'm Komiya.
So, Mr. Zaitsu, how do you…
What do you do to take care
of your mental health?
Uh…
You see, I'm a short-distance runner
struggling with anxiety,
and it's now affecting my running.
When I was a kid,
I ended up hurting my leg.
Even though it's completely healed,
whenever I reach my top speed,
it always seems to slow down.
But then… uh…
Do you know of any solutions to fix that?
Well, the bottom line is,
you don't have to cope with your anxiety.
This world is filled
with possibilities of failure,
but the thing is,
that's what gives life its charm.
Fear isn't unpleasant,
and safety isn't always pleasant.
Anxiety is a feeling one gets
when one challenges themselves.
So, if one must sacrifice
something for victory,
then give up your body because it's just
a collection of cells. Glory is forever.
So, what goal are you trying to achieve?
Someday, I would like to be
the national record holder.
[gasps, chatter]
I see. What was your name?
-It's Komiya.
-[whistle blows]
[gasping]
-[gasps]
[gasps]
That new guy's one to watch out for.
Uh-huh.
[coach] Thanks
for everything today, Zaitsu.
Did the students behave?
Yes.
[coach] Is coffee okay?
[Zaitsu] Yes, thank you, sir.
That one. He's fast.
Mm.
Ah.
Tsuneda, right?
He's second-year,
but he's ranked first in Kyushu.
All of Japan is going to know him
by this year's inter high.
I suppose they will.
It's only a matter of time.
We'll see who the real gem is.
[grunts]
Well, it looks like
someone's figured it out.
You've overcome your hurdles, huh?
I have.
Still, you shouldn't overtrain.
You should head home for today.
Well, my legs are still
feeling pretty fresh.
So, I'm gonna train some more
before going home.
The very first time I saw you run,
I noticed your right leg had issues.
Zaitsu's advice
helped me overcome all that.
So it seems.
I know that it really isn't my place
to tell you this.
But… you should give up
on your dreams of running.
Haven't you realized it yet?
That your running form
is not sustainable, at all!
Yeah, sure, yes, you're getting faster.
But at what cost?
There's only one reason
you're able to run like that!
It's all passion!
That's a red flag!
A runner who ignores
their physical limitations
through sheer will doesn't have brakes!
Victory will never be enough!
They'll keep going until it destroys them!
Your yips must have been your body
trying to want you to quit!
[seethes]
Running will be the end of you.
So what you're saying is,
even someone like me
has a shot at a moment of glory.
Are you kidding me?
That's what you got from that?
Thanks, Captain.
Wait, hold on!
[crowd cheering]
[spectator 1] That's insane!
[spectator 1] Who the heck is he?
[spectator 2] I'm not sure,
but he just beat Tsuneda's record.
[girl] Komiya, hey!
Congrats getting the top spot
in the qualifiers.
It was so insane how fast you were.
I bet you or Tsuneda
will win the whole thing.
Oh man. I didn't even think
about which one of them
I should be rooting for in the finals.
[girl chuckles] We should
just cheer both of them on.
[boy chuckles] Oh, right.
[chuckles]
Sorry, we didn't mean to hold you up.
-It's fine. Later.
-[chuckles]
Good luck in the final!
NATIONAL HS CHAMPIONSHIPS
BOYS' 100M REGIONAL FINAL
[race starter] On your marks.
Set…
[crowd cheering]
KOMIYA TSUNEDA
NATIONAL HIGH SCHOOL CHAMPIONSHIPS
Nigami.
Hey.
[Nigami] Gotta make it past the prelims.
[Togashi] Sure do.
[groans]
[sighs] It's hard to believe
that my back is actually still holding up.
I'm gonna give it all I've got.
Good.
Alright. See ya.
Yeah.
[door clicks open]
[door clicks shut]
KOMIYA
[pensive music]
[race starter] On your marks.
[crowd cheering]
[groaning]
[starting block clanks]
[race starter] Set…
[clang]
[crowd cheering]
[gasping]
-[clang]
-[gasps]
Nigami, nice work out there.
You almost had it.
Nah, it wasn't even close.
Great job.
Congratulations, Togashi.
You heard, right? You broke a record.
The wind really helped me.
But I felt good out there.
I'd hoped we could've raced one last time.
But regardless, I feel good too.
You were a great competitor, Nigami.
You should watch out for that Komiya guy.
He's impossibly fast.
Yeah, I saw.
If he didn't ease off toward the end,
he probably could've…
Long time no see.
Likewise.
I see you kept up with track.
Hmm.
It's been a while
since the last time we raced.
I'm gonna win this one too.
I see. I wish you luck.
EVACUATION ROUTE OVERVIEW
[exhilarating music]
[shutters clicking]
[announcer] In lane one, Matsuba
from Utsugikita High, Hiroshima.
In lane two, Nakanishi,
from Suzuna Chuo High, Osaka.
In lane three… [indistinct]
from Natamame High, Shizuoka.
In lane four, Komiya
from Nishizawa High, Oita.
In lane five, Togashi
from Iwashi Daini High, Tokyo.
[inaudible]
On your marks.
[dynamic music ends]
[race starter] Set…
[whirring]
[crowd cheering]
[whoosh]
[breathing heavily]
[gasping]
Togashi, your running style changed.
[rain thundering increasingly]
[rain thundering]
TEN YEARS LATER
[hooter honking]
[crosswalk signal beeping]
Alright, so, after taking
your performance into account…
[gulps]
[man] …we've decided
to renew your contract.
[sighs] Yes!
Oh, thank goodness.
I can relax now.
Yes, well, Togashi.
Listen, I hate to bring this up,
but let's keep in mind
that you just barely made the cut, okay?
This is a key year for you.
Right. I'll be sure
to do my best, sir. Thanks.
[Togashi] Alright, then.
[sighs]
[groans softly]
-Oh. Hey, wait!
-Yes, sir?
I forgot to give this to you.
It'd be great if you could join us
for this next month.
Company event?
Yes. Kaido and Kabaki
are also planning on attending.
Perhaps you can get some pointers
and or advice from those two.
Advice about what exactly?
Oh, well, you know, you're not
quite the athlete you once were.
They might be able
to help you with your comeback.
Ah. Right. Yeah. [chuckles]
[footsteps approaching]
[Togashi] Hey, Kabaki, morning.
Hey, Togashi. Good morning to you too.
Well, I got my contract renewed.
But only just barely.
That's good to hear.
-Togashi.
-Hmm?
You've changed a lot.
What?
I've been watching you run
ever since I was a kid.
You're completely different now.
[chuckles] Well…
Don't remind me, man.
I know I'm not who I used to be.
This could be my last year, so I'm
just doing my best.
[upbeat music]
[panting]
[grunts softly]
[dynamic music]
[clang]
[crowd cheering]
[panting]
It's obvious I wasn't in top form today,
but I'll remind you
the season's only just started.
I'll do what I can to improve day by day.
JAPAN TRACK-AND-FIELD
NATIONAL CHAMPIONSHIPS
[train rumbling]
KUSASHINO CORP.
TRACK AND FIELD GATHERING
The popularity of track and field
has grown rapidly.
As a company, we have been supporting
the athletes who are competing
at the very top of their field.
And now, it's my pleasure
to invite to the stage
an athlete
who is well known for his talents,
and who has been competing
in major short-distance races
for the last 15 years.
Put your hands together for Mr. Kaido.
[applause]
Hi. Thanks, everyone.
Although it's true
that I've been doing this for a while now,
I still think that I'm in my prime.
I've been striving to continue
beating my personal best every year.
Because there's one thing
that I know for sure.
Cold, hard reality
won't get rewritten on its own.
So, this year, I'll deal
with this reality,
where Zaitsu's been sitting
on the throne for too long.
That's all I have to say.
Very well said.
Thank you for your inspirational words,
Mr. Kaido.
How to deal with reality?
Yes.
There's only one way to do it.
You just have to break records.
Thought you'd say that.
But… Well…
It's easier said than done, sir.
That's no excuse.
I never took you for a quitter.
I'm not saying I am.
It's just… I'm not getting any younger.
Yeah, I get you.
Well, I don't have
a straight answer for that, Togashi.
But I can share my story with you.
Ever since I was a kid,
I knew for a fact that I was talented.
Running always came easy to me.
And short distances were my specialty.
I was the fastest in my region.
I never lost a single race to anyone.
Then I got my ass kicked
for the first time at nationals,
which only made me train even harder.
It paid off.
In my last year of high school,
I nearly won at nationals.
[Kaido] Then a first-year
named Zaitsu showed up.
Since that day 15 years ago,
I've been forced
to keep on living this new reality.
It's one where Zaitsu
has always been one step ahead.
A reality where I never win.
And earned the nickname "Forever Second."
[scoffs]
A reality where I keep aging
by the second,
while a new young gun named Komiya
is rising to the top.
[scoffs] Though he's not that young now.
[chuckles]
I'm sick of hearing that it's a shame
that I wasn't born in another era.
It's kind of funny.
I'm just drowning here in this world
that won't let me win.
But it never deters me from trying to win
because I'm confident
I have a real chance to win the next one.
Do you know why that is?
No.
Because you can escape from reality.
What?
If winning a race
isn't possible for me here,
then I'll just do all I can
to escape this reality.
And doing that means
I still have hope for myself.
It means that my attitude in life
is to not give up on me.
There might be other opinions out there,
insights, truths too,
even enlightenment getting thrown around.
I only recognize my own.
That's the duty I have to myself.
My meaning in life, the reason I run.
Listen, Togashi.
As long as you understand why you run,
then you can escape any reality you're in.
-Kaido, this is Sekiguchi.
-[grunts]
She's one of our newest staff members.
-Hello.
-[Sekiguchi] Hello, sir.
I'm Sekiguchi. I'm so honored to meet you.
[automobile revving]
[clock ticking]
[journalist] So does this mean
you intend to keep running
for the foreseeable future?
Yes.
Though I'd love to start fresh.
I want to do my best and not be judged
by who I was in the past.
Speaking of athletes your age,
what are your thoughts on Komiya,
who's a rising star and considered
to be the next face of track and field?
Uh, what can I say?
All I know is I'd like
to compete against him again.
Well then, on that note,
my last question to you is,
what's your reason you continue to run?
What's my reason?
[sighs] Good question.
Sorry, are you Mr. Togashi?
-Yes.
-Nice to meet you.
Nice to meet you too.
It's an honor. My name is Morikawa.
Morikawa, huh?
You won the high school nationals
last year, right?
That's right. You know who I am?
This is so cool!
Huge fan. You inspired me
to get into track and field.
Um… Could I maybe shake your hand?
Oh. Of course.
Ah! Thank you so much!
[chuckles]
[crowd cheering]
[spectator] Come on! Go on! Go, go, go!
[Kaido] Hey, Togashi.
Oh, Mr. Kaido.
Thank you so much
for your advice the other day.
How are things going with you?
I've been figuring things out.
It's starting to make sense to me.
I've realized the real reason
that I run isn't to win,
but for the sake of others out there.
That's my ticket to escaping reality.
You don't say.
[sighs]
That's good. Everyone should try
to find their own answer.
But would you like to know what I think?
Until you understand your own reality,
there's no way
you can really escape from it.
Standing with your eyes closed to reality
is totally different
from running with them wide open.
Looking straight into reality
can be extremely terrifying.
You have to accept the things
you don't want to accept.
[pensive music]
But if you truly wanna reject any reality,
then you must face it head on,
with your eyes wide open.
If your eyes are closed,
you can't run anywhere.
You're just gonna stay standing still.
Watch yourself, Togashi.
I will.
[energetic up-tempo music]
-Oh, Togashi! So glad I caught you!
-[gasps]
Nice job. Number two!
You pretty much tied with Kabaki.
You cleared the B-qualifying standard.
Way to go!
-[laughs]
-[chuckles]
I appreciate it, sir.
Frankly, it was totally unexpected.
Yeah. I agree.
I know, right?
[laughs]
Now that you're officially qualified
and competing in the track
and field championships this year,
I can't wait to see your comeback.
I'll be watching.
-Thank you. I'll have to do my best.
-[laughs] Ha-ha! This is gonna be great!
[runner 1] Hey, Togashi.
Good to see you today.
-How's it going with you?
-[runner 2] Pretty good. Can't complain.
[race starter] Get set…
[clang]
KOYAMACHO HOSPITAL
[doctor] Looks like a muscle strain.
Huh?
It'd be in your best interest
not to participate in the meet this year.
Uh, but the national championships
are a week away.
Togashi, you can't take
a muscle strain like this lightly.
If you keep pushing it, the muscles
in your leg will get completely torn,
and your career will be over.
Doctor, I have to compete this year.
I understand that, but six months of rehab
is what's best for you in the long-term.
Just concentrate on a full recovery
for the time being.
There's always next year…
[tense music]
What?
I'm sorry to hear about your leg injury,
but if you're unable
to compete in the next meet,
we unfortunately will have to let you go.
You can't be serious.
I'm very serious.
If you look in the contract,
it's all right there.
However, we recognize your efforts
and appreciate everything
you've done for us so far.
Therefore, we'd like
to offer you the opportunity
to continue supporting us as
a track and field coach from here on out.
Take your time to read through the terms,
and if you're happy with it,
then we can make it official by drafting…
[children chattering]
[boy] That form looked good.
Think we can beat class four now?
Hey, maybe we'll be better
if we took bigger steps.
It might help us run faster.
-[Togashi] It's the opposite.
-Huh?
Making your strides too wide
will mess up your balance.
Oh… Sorry. I didn't mean to intrude.
Uh, what do you mean by strides, mister?
Right.
So, instead of extending
your legs forward,
push your feet against the ground
with each step.
Really try to push down.
Push my feet down?
Yeah, just like that.
Nice. Let's try it out.
Yeah. Thanks for the tips, mister.
We really appreciate it.
-It's Sports Day soon, isn't it?
-[both] Yeah.
He's our anchor,
and I'm running right before him.
We really want to beat class four.
I see. You've got a rival
in class four, don't you?
Listen. Learning to deal
with defeats in your life
is far more important than any technique.
Huh?
Sometimes, even though
you give it your all,
you can still be defeated.
It's okay if you don't win.
And it's not like your whole life ends
if you end up losing.
If you're prepared to lose,
sometimes it can help you perform better.
Speed isn't everything.
-Uh…
-So, take it easy.
[sobbing]
Why should you sacrifice everything?
Your entire life…
[sobbing]
[groaning]
-Oh, geez.
-Let's get out of here.
Yeah.
[boys panting]
[sobbing ends]
[car passing]
AIDA HOSPITAL
-[Nigami] Togashi!
-Hm?
Hey, Nigami.
Can I give you a lift?
[Togashi] Thank you so much
for introducing me to a good doctor.
Of course. I can't believe
the race is only a week away.
I can do this.
All I have to do is run
three more times, that's it.
You remind me of how I used to be
back in high school.
I was so scared back then.
You know, I was totally ready
to throw away my entire life
just for that one brief moment.
Before I even noticed,
I died inside living for tomorrow.
The next race represents
25 years of my life
and where I'm now.
But I think I realized something.
If I keep living for yesterday,
I'll never be able to be in the present
and give it everything I've got.
[journalist]
How are you feeling, Mr. Kabaki?
Doing okay, I guess.
Today's prelim is like a warm-up
for tomorrow's finals, so I'm just…
Hey, Kabaki. Morning.
Oh, good morning.
I heard that you got injured.
Is your leg alright?
[scoffs]
Not in the clear yet,
but I can manage for now.
Okay, then.
Well, see you out there.
Sure.
Mr. Togashi's competing
in your heat, isn't he?
How are you feeling
about the upcoming final?
This completely changes everything.
It'll be a tight race.
[crowd cheering]
[commentator] Kabaki takes the win,
and Togashi comes in second.
[chuckles]
I see you're always
well prepared, aren't you?
Mr. Zaitsu.
I heard that you had
an easy win in the prelims.
You did too.
Feels like it was so long ago
when you asked me
about mental health and anxiety.
Your advice
really helped me out back then.
I now have a clear goal thanks to you.
A goal, huh?
Yeah.
Stats and formulas, trends and strategy.
My goal of breaking these records
is so much greater than your numbers.
I know that I'll win.
Well, that's impressive, for staking
your entire life to set a record.
Are you complimenting me?
I feel sorry for you.
Over time,
I lost my fighting spirit
in exchange for a title,
undisputed champion.
The faster I go,
the more everyone falls behind.
When I look beside me, no one's there.
The view from that position
is the same as from last place.
And nothing is more boring than that.
The thing that is a true triumph
and what brings us pure joy
is neither medals nor records.
It's the person you run against.
Having others
you can actually compete with,
-that's the real--
-Thanks, but…
I have my own way.
Right. Of course you do.
[suspenseful music]
Can't wait to see you out there.
[commentator] Here's the first heat
of the men's 100-meter semi-final.
Kabaki is a clear favorite to win today,
but can't forget about Togashi.
And with these two competing, can the new
17-year-old Morikawa keep up with them?
[race starter] Set…
[crowd cheering]
[commentator] Togashi in first!
Kabaki in second!
Morikawa comes in with a close third!
[woman] Zaitsu, Komiya, and Kaido?
It looks like Japan's
current top three are all here.
Well, it's basically the finals.
Everyone seems to agree that Zaitsu's
been kind of on the decline lately.
So, I think that Komiya's
got a good chance of winning this year.
That's only 'cause Zaitsu
had an unusual prime.
But I still think
he's got some fire left in him.
Either way,
I'm pretty sure
Zaitsu or Komiya's gonna win.
I agree. It's gotta be Zaitsu or Komiya.
Zaitsu or Komiya.
-Zaitsu or Komiya.
Zaitsu or Komiya. Zaitsu or Komiya.
[chuckles]
Does this mean I'm not in the game?
[commentator] Heat two of the semi-finals
will begin momentarily.
How will Kaido handle himself
against Zaitsu and Komiya?
-Let's wait and see.
-[race starter] On your marks.
[breathes deeply]
[race starter] Set…
-[clang]
-[dynamic up-tempo music]
[Kaido] I see. So this is my reality.
[scoffs]
Well, then. If that's the case,
it's time to escape from reality.
[commentator] Kaido takes the win!
Komiya in second!
And Zaitsu ends up in fifth.
Can you believe it?
Zaitsu's been eliminated
in the semi-finals.
Kaido has finally defeated Zaitsu.
Not only that, but Kaido's time today
is the second best
in Japan's entire history.
[crowd muttering]
[Togashi] Komiya.
It's good to see you again.
Long time no see.
It's been ten years.
We finally get the chance
to run against each other again.
Yeah.
Togashi, have you ever wondered about it?
What the point is of running
the same distance every day?
I've had one clear goal.
I've been thinking about nothing else
but setting records.
For the last ten years,
that's all I've really cared about.
Just now, though,
my record was beaten by someone
who doesn't even care about records.
Without any calculations
and with no trends or strategy,
his tenacity was his sole driving force.
In the end,
even if I set some new records,
I'm not sure
what waits for me beyond that.
You gain nothing by being fast,
lose nothing by being slow,
so maybe it's all for nothing.
And if that's the case,
then what is that brief moment for?
And why are we even competing
in this race?
What is the point of it?
Why do we continue to run?
It's obvious, isn't it?
For us to give it our all,
no other reason.
When I reflect back on things,
I realize how stressful my life's been.
I was afraid of losing and being alone.
Then I thought I was unbeatable.
And so, I refused to face my defeats.
I had this odd faith
that someone was watching over me.
But my past led me here.
Every person knows themselves
the best out of anyone.
And there's no place anyone truly belongs.
Confidence, empathy, and affection
are all things created by your mind.
Even anxiety,
which we always feel in this life.
And ultimately, we all die in the end.
If you think about it,
we're all a little messed up.
But with all that said…
none of these things matter.
Nothing takes away the joy
of when we give our all.
I know that because I've witnessed it
countless times in others.
And I felt it myself.
I'm sorry, but I've never experienced
anything like that.
Not once in my lifetime.
The emptiness that I feel has no solution.
Komiya, you seem to have forgotten
the one simple rule I said
when we were younger.
That is…
running the 100-meter dash faster
than anyone can solve almost anything.
[groans]
You're incredibly fast,
and you found success
because you put in the hard work
and invested in yourself.
Was all that pointless?
When we run and give our best,
the world sharpens,
and everything starts to shine.
If you haven't experienced
that feeling yet,
let's witness it together
in the next 100 meters.
Mr. Zaitsu, we saw you suddenly slow down.
Did you get injured out there today?
Were you in some accident?
Everyone, there's something
I'd like to announce.
I'm sorry, but as of today,
I'm officially retiring.
What? Really?
Did you just say you were retiring?
But…
[grunts, groans]
[clamoring]
-Wait, this is serious.
-Hey, guys!
-Zaitsu says he's retiring…
-[overlapping chatter]
-Yeah, get over here!
-Is this because of your loss earlier?
Or do you have an injury?
Since I'm retiring, I can speak freely now
and express how I truly feel.
The 100 meters
condenses a whole life
into a single moment.
Just a couple of centimeters
can be the thing that destroys you.
However,
that's the reason why we feel euphoria.
A wealth of things can be found
in merely that distance.
[journalist] We're coming to you live
here with Mr. Zaitsu,
who's just announced his retirement.
-[reporter] Wait, wait, Mr. Zaitsu!
-[reporters clamoring]
-[clamoring]
-[reporter] One more question!
Any words of wisdom to share
with those competing in the final?
Hope. Glory.
Disappointment. Setback.
Fatigue. Satisfaction.
Frustration. Achievement.
Along with every other feeling.
Stuff every one of them
into the 100 meters
and savor the finest ten seconds
of your life.
[reporters clamoring]
[cat purring]
[pensive music]
ALARM
OKRA HOTEL
[birds chirping]
[commentator] Day two
at the national championships.
Next, the men's 100-meter final.
Zaitsu, known as the king
of the 100 meters,
was eliminated in the semis
and shockingly announced
his retirement yesterday.
The history of track and field
is about to change.
[indistinct chattering]
[commentator] Get ready, folks, as we will
all witness history being made tonight.
Who will be crowned as the fastest man?
The national championship
men's 100-meter final starts…
now.
[rhythmic thumping]
PLEASE KEEP QUIET DURING THE START!
[tense music]
[race starter] On your marks.
THE FINAL RACE
WILL BE FINISHED
[race starter] Set…
IN TEN SECONDS
[clang]
[crowd cheering]
[heavy breathing]
[gasping]
[rapid footsteps]
[upbeat music]